<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise of vsurie, made by Nicolas Sander D. of Diuinitie</title>
            <title>Briefe treatise of usurie.</title>
            <author>Sander, Nicholas, 1530?-1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1568</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105179</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840908</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840908</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5452</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5452)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 937:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise of vsurie, made by Nicolas Sander D. of Diuinitie</title>
                  <title>Briefe treatise of usurie.</title>
                  <author>Sander, Nicholas, 1530?-1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 67, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Apud Ioannem Foulerum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Louanii :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1568. Cum priuilegio. Subsig. De La Torre.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of usurie.</note>
                  <note>Errata on I6v.</note>
                  <note>Two pages of Latin notes in contemporary manuscript hand follow I7.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE <hi>TREATISE OF VSVRIE, MADE BY</hi> Nicolas Sander D. of <hi>Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luc. 6.</bibl>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mutuum date, nihil inde ſperantes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Geue to lone, hoping for nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g therof.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <p>RESPICITE VOLATILIA COELI, ET PVLLOS CORVORVM</p>
               <p>I F</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LOVANII, <hi>Apud Ioannem Foulerum, An.</hi> 1568. Cum Priuilegio. Subſig. <hi>De La Torre.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5452:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISE <hi>OF VSVRIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The occaſion of this Treatiſe, and the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vvhich are commonly made for the defenſe of vſurie, and vvhat is vſurie. The firſt Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did not intrude my ſelfe (good Reader) to make this Treatiſe, but was forced ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, by verie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie: except I would wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer my Chriſtian brethern to runne hedlong into vice, and to defend that for lawful, which is vtterly againſt the ordinance of God. And ſuerly when I ſaw, that a ſinne was not only committed (which cometh of the frayltie of man) but was alſo defended: then
<pb facs="tcp:5452:3"/>
I tought it my dutie, not to holde my penne any longer.</p>
               <p>The matter I ſpeake of, is vſurie, in defence whereof thus I haue heard diuerſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon at ſeueral tymes. I haue (ſayeth he) a poore ſtocke of money lawfully gotten, it lyeth by me idely, and it will quickly be ſpent, if it be not occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied. I was not brought vp in the trade of merchandiſe, I haue wife and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who are like to begge, vnleſſe I prouide ſome perpetuall reliefe for them. In this caſe what ſhal I do with my money but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye it ſo, that it might not be loſt, and yet might bring me ſome yearely profite?</p>
               <p>Agayne, I lend it to ſuch a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant whom I knowe to take co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie and no hurt therby: why then may I not take profite of mine owne money <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogether with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5452:3"/>
him? or why ſhould he enrich him ſelfe with my money, and not be bounde to geue me ſome part of his gaine? Hereunto when I made anſwer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.</note> that the word of God did forbid vſurie: he replied, that he thought it was rather a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in Gods word to auoyde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme taking of vſurie, then any ſuch precept as bound men to the obedience therof vnder the paine of euerlaſting damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nay (ſaid I) that can not be ſo. For the Church hath taken it to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement which muſt be kept vnder the paine of damnation,<note place="margin">Sub Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro tertio. in Concil. Lateraneſt c. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> and thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath forbidden open v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers to be admitted to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the altare, and to be buried in holy ground, and their offerings to be receaued, vnder the paine of ſuſpenſion to him that burieth, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els receaueth their oblations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:4"/>Here began a new diſputation, which is the true Churche, and what power poſitiue lawes haue. Yea the word of God (according to theſe new interpretations) is al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo brought forth, that ſuch vſurie as byteth him ſore who boroweth, is in dede forbidden (for in the Hebrew vſurie is named of by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) but not ſuche as doth bring commoditie, as well to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, as to the lender. I wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſee what ſhift the deuill made, to maintaine that moſt hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſe crime of vſurie, in ſo much that he hath found the pretenſe of holy ſcripture and of Gods word for it.</p>
               <p>To make ſhort the diſputation, and to cut of th'vnprofitable talke of wordes and names, I ſayd at the laſt (which nowe God willing I wil proue) vſurie is vtterly againſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5452:4"/>
God and Nature, euen as mankil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is. And therefore whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the holy Scripture or the Catholike Churche hath decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereof, yt hath decreed yt as againſt one of the greateſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſinnes that can be. So that nowe it is my part to ſhewe, how vſurie is not only againſt the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God expreſſed in the holy ſcriptures, but alſo againſt his will and commaundement: the breach whereof is euerlaſting death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it ſhall appere both by the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the places wherein it is forbidden, and alſo by the reaſon of the forbidding, this only being firſt knowen: that,<note place="margin">VVhat is vſurie.</note> 
                  <hi>vſurie is all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of gaines, which is either bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained or hoped for by the force of the contract of geuing to lone, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther monie be lent, or oile, corne, wine, or any like thing that is ſpent
<pb facs="tcp:5452:5"/>
with the firſt natural and proper vſe thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> for when the vſe of that thing which can be but once vſed of the borower without the ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof and which by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deliuery to thend it may be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">Real vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> is alienated from the lender, is payed for: that is real vſurie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and when the lender hath a deſire to be paid for the vſe of that thing,<note place="margin">Mentall vſurie.</note> that is mental vſurie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>That vſurie is forbidden by Gods lavve, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paine of euerlaſting damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The ſecond Chapiter.</head>
               <p>IF men had now that obedience and faith which they once had, and ſtil ſhould haue: it had ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to haue ſayed in one woorde, <hi>The Church condemneth vſurie, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5452:5"/>
forbiddeth it as a mortal ſinne. He that heareth not the Churche,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>is to be taken as an heathen and a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican.</hi> But nowe if we anſwer ſo, they will demaund which is the true Church, where is it, or how can we be aſſured, that it erreth not? For whiche cauſe I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, to geue an accompt of the Churches doctrine touching vſurie.</p>
               <p>And for as muche as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Church being once called into queſtion, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo (whiche were geuen onely to the Churche, and are knowen by her tradition, and by her vnwritten witneſſe) can not keepe their creditte, but are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded accordinge to euerie mans luſt and phantaſie: I muſt alſo be forced, to reſort vnto na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural reaſon, and thereby to ſhew,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that vſurie is of it ſelfe naught and vniuſt. For albeit the rule of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may not ſtil be folowed, for as much as the articles of our faithe depend not vppon natural reaſon which is common to all men, but vpon the reuelation of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> who powreth his giftes into the hartes of the faithfull abundantly: yet nowe it ſhall not be amiſſe to proue, that vſurie is againſt natural reaſon, becauſe it is a matter of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie and of ciuil iniuſtice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of reaſon may iudge. But who ſo is not able to reache vnto the depth of reaſon, that he may at the leaſt not lacke the authoritie of Gods word: I wil firſt declare, that the word of God ſheweth vſurie to be a great ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.</note>It is written in the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after this ſort: <hi>Si pecuniam mutuam dederis populo meo pauperi
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5452:6"/>
qui habitat tecum, non vrgebis eum quaſi exactor, nec vſuris opprimes.</hi> If thou ſhalt geue monie to lone vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my poore people which dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with thee, thou ſhalt not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant vpon him as an importunate wringer, neither ſhalt thou op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe him with vſurie. Firſt this precept ſtandeth emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preceptes, which are to be kept of neceſsitie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.</note> For a litle before it is forbidden, that <hi>witches ſhould be ſuffered to lyue, or thoſe that had lyen with beastes, or thoſe that ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice to any, ſauing to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</hi> The people were alſo forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>to hurt a childe, or a widow.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which preceptes, this of vſurie foloweth.</p>
               <p>Seing then it is ioyned with thoſe commaundements, which if they be not kept, the breaker is guyltie of euerlaſting death: we
<pb facs="tcp:5452:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
muſt thinke alſo the verie ſame of vſurie. Neither may it iuſtly be layed againſt me, that not euerie vſurie is forbidden, but onely that whiche wringeth and byteth the poore: for both euerie vſurie dooth wring and byte, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie lending ought to be made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore. For lending is a kind of charitie, or of almoſedeedes, which was inſtituted chiefely and only for the poore. Who ſeeth not then, that it is an abuſe to lend monie to him, who hath as much, or more, then he that lendeth yt?</p>
               <p>If then thou lend to the poore, ſaith God (meaning, that for other men the contract of lending was not made) thou ſhalt not byte him nor wring him. To lende vnto the poore, that is in dede a counſel ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a precept, and therefore it is not ſaid, thou ſhalt lend monie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5452:7"/>
to the poore man. But if thou doe lend him mony, it is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, not to take vſurie of him, becauſe that were to wring him, and to byte him. Now as it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be but a great fault, to wring or byte any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo is it much more, to wring or byte him, who is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die poore and miſerable.</p>
               <p>Moreouer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit,</hi> 25<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> this precept is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by another lyke place. If thy brother be impoueriſhed, <hi>ne accipias vſuras ab eo, nec amplius quàm dediſti</hi> take thou no vſurie of him, nor any more then thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt delyuer. Here he is called our brother, which before was called Gods poore people: and, whome we were forbidden to wringe or byte, of him we are nowe forbidden, to take any more, then we deliuerid vnto him. For he that taketh one pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny more,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:8"/>
then he delyuered: wringeth and byteth him, aſmuch as that penny cometh to.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.</note>Agayne God ſayeth: <hi>Non foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabis fratri tuo ad vſuram pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam, nec fruges; nec quamlibet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam rem, ſed alieno.</hi> Thou ſhalt not increaſe monie vpon thy brother by vſurie, nor corne, nor any other thing: but do that to thine enemy. <hi>Fratri autem tuo, aſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vſura, id quod indiget, commodabis.</hi> Thou ſhalt le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy brother that whiche he lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, without vſurie. The carnall Iewes had certain infidels to their enemies: whom as they might kil, ſo might they oppreſſe them with vſurie. But now ſeing euerie man is both our neighbour, and our brother: we may not take vſurie of any man at al.</p>
               <p>It is here farther to be noted, that vſurie conſiſteth not only in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5452:8"/>
taking gaynes of monie, but alſo in corne, or any other kynd of thing whiche may be geuen to lone, as it ſhal afterward be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For al that which by the way of lone is hoaped to be reſtored aboue that which was lent, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the lender guyltie of vſurie, and conſequently of death, as in Ezechiel alſo we reade:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezec.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Dans ad vſuram &amp; amplius accipiens, non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet.</hi> He that geueth (his monie or wares) to vſurie, and taketh more (then he gaue) ſhal not lyue. That is to ſay, he ſhal not enioy heauen, without he repent him of it.</p>
               <p>Alſo when <hi>Dauid</hi> had aſked,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.</note> who ſhould dwel in our Lordes taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, he anſwereth (emong other thinges) <hi>he that hath not geuen his monie to vſurie,</hi> meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath geuen his monie to vſurie, ſhall not dwel with God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Laſt of al Chriſt him ſelfe ſaith: <hi>Date mutuum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>nihil inde ſperantes,</hi> geue to lone, hoaping for nothing out of the lone it ſelfe, or in the reſpect thereof. Where, not only expreſſe bargaines for vſurie: but al hope alſo and expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gayne to ryſe therby, is vtterly forbidden. For the verie greedines to receaue gayne by a liberal and free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, maketh a man to be a ſynner in the ſight of God: becauſe for his part he turneth a free and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble contract into the moſt wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and hurtful bargaine that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be. For wherin he ſhould haue ayded the poore, therein he oppreſſeth them. And where he ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue loſt ſomewhat of his owne for Gods ſake, there he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth his owne, and taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s goods iniuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as it ſhal more plainly appeare,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5452:9"/>
when the matter of geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to lone is fully declared. For this prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vſurie in Gods lawe, is but the opening and making playne of the law of nature in that behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>VVhence bargaines proceede, and vvhy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſdedes are ſo acceptable to God. The third Chapiter.</head>
               <p>SVche bargaines, couenantes, contractes, and obligations, as do vſually paſſe emong men, either proceede from liberalitie, or els from the neceſſarie vſe of trafique. Thoſe procede from libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, wherein the one partie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone taketh commoditie, as in all free giftes and legacies. But thoſe bargaines which are practiſed to and fro, for the neceſsitie of eche partie, ought to bring loſſe or gaine equally to eche of them: as
<pb facs="tcp:5452:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in byeng and ſelling, ſetting, and ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king to hyer, in felowſhip of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe, and in ſuch like caſes it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe. My purpoſe is at this time to ſpeake only of the firſt kind of couenantes, and yet not of all them, but ſpecially of geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to lone or lending, which in Latin is called <hi>Mutuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Now albeit a donation or free gift, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is really deliuered, is not properly a contract: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many times a man bindeth him ſelfe by ſolemne promiſe afore hand, to geue a thing afterward, in this caſe there is a certain couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwen them, which muſt be kept. Once that kind of doing or of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining, which is moſt liberall, or hath leaſt hope of gaine or reward to be returned, is of all other moſt acceptable to God, and moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable in it ſelf, as coming nigheſt to the nature and worki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5452:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
God:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> who firſt geuing vs freely faith and charitie, wherby we may do his will: afterward promiſeth, and wil geue vs life euerlaſting, if we beleue in him, and with his grace do kepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. And yet for al this he looketh for no commoditie, by our faith or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 17.</note> but <hi>we are ſtil vnprofitable ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes,</hi> as touching any gaine that may riſe to him by our ſeruice: but only he of his botomeleſſe mercie ſpreadeth his goodnes vpon vs, to enrich our miſerable pouerty with his vnſpeakable treaſures and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For this cauſe Almoſdedes are ſo much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: as in the which we geue and preſently deliuer, or bynde our ſelues to geue and to deliuer our ſuperfluouſe or profitable goodes, to our poore neighbours for Gods ſake, and that although there be no
<pb facs="tcp:5452:11"/>
hoape to receaue lyke kyndneſſe againe of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 11.</note>A certaine Phariſeie did on a time bid Chriſt to diner, and when he ſawe Chriſt ſit downe before he had waſhed, he wondered not a litle at yt. Then ſayed our Lord to him: <hi>Now yee Phariſies do make cleane the outmoſt part of the cup and of the platter, but that which is within you, is ful of rauening and of iniquitie. Ye fooles, did not he who made that which is without, make alſo that with is within? Howbeit geue almoſe of that which is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus in you, and lo, al thinges are cleane vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which teſtimonie the truth it ſelfe doth witneſſe, that euen our dayly ſinnes and inward vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, are made cleane by Almoſdedes. And therfore when <hi>Zacheus</hi> had ſaied, <hi>Behold, I geue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5452:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
halfe my goodes to the poore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and if I haue deceaued any man, I reſtore fower dubble: Ieſus anſwered, that the ſame day ſaluation was made to that houſe, for that he alſo was made the ſonne of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Yea the very perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a faithful man is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt to conſiſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>in ſelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way al thinges that he hath, and in geuing yt to the poore. Which who ſo doth and foloweth Chriſt, ſhal haue a treaſure in heauen.</hi> In ſo much that on the day of Iudgement Chriſt ſheweth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> that <hi>thoſe who haue done the workes of mercie, for his ſake, ſhall haue heauen for their reward, and thoſe who haue not done them, ſhal go into hel fyer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being ſo, yt ſhould not ſeme any vnwonted ſute to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men, if I ſhould exhorte them to geue away al their goodes to others who lacke, and ſo to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb facs="tcp:5452:12"/>
Chriſt. But now I aſke not ſo much. It is now no world wherein to require any ſuch perfection. I would thinke my ſelfe happy, if I were able to perſuade men to geue away onely that which they haue ſuperfluous and more then is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Nay neither that do I now aſke which yet in caſes of other mens neede, they are bound to do. But I aſke and beſeche men only to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde and eſchew thoſe, whiche are extreme great ſinnes, and moſt enemies to Almoſdedes, I meane, vſury, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Symony. Of which Symo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in ſpirituall cauſes, vſury in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſecular matters. Of Symony I wil not ſpeak, either becauſe the matter is not ſo hard, or intricate, and therefore is not lightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted but vpon malice, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly is incurable: or els becauſe thoſe of the clergie, who moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly are the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5452:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
into that horrible vice, are them ſelues, or at the leaſt ſhould be ſo farre lerned,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8.</note> as to know that <hi>Symo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Magus</hi> (vnleſſe he repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted) had the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by <hi>S. Peter</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, becauſe he went about to bie the giftes of the holy Ghoſt with money. And he that bieth or ſelleth a benefice, or any thing wherevnto the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the giftes of the holy Ghoſt is annexed, is in the ſame caſe for his degree with <hi>Symo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Magꝰ,</hi> except he ſo repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as he ought to do, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be abſolued according as the Church hath euer vſed to abſolue ſuch cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. But the matter of vſury is not ſo eaſie to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as that of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and therefore it needeth a longer diſcourſe to declare the iniquitie thereof, which being one of the verie greateſt, yet through the ignorance or blyndneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:5452:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
men, is now growen out of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and is taken to be either none at al, or ſuerly no verie great fault. But how can that be a ſmal fault, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to ſo great a vertue as almoſdeedes is? Truth muſt be heard with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, good Reader.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Proue.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>The woundes of him that loueth, are better then the deceitfull kyſſes of him that hateth.</hi> Vſurie of it ſelfe is more contrarie to almoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes, then commonly robberie or theft is: becauſe theft is moſt tymes committed of them that lacke, but vſurie is committed on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of them who are riche. The theefe as nighe as he can, wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer robbe a poore man: the vſurer doth commonly robbe poore men moſt of al. Theft is puniſhed by ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lawes, vſurie is winked at, becauſe it is a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>till manly theft. Al men are aſhamed of theft, but many men
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5452:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
profeſſe vſury, and bluſh not much at yt, for that euil cuſtome hath ſo long tyme borne with it. I ſpeake not this of al kind of vſurers, but of the worſt ſort of them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as yet there is none at al good. But there is great oddes betwene ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bargaining for vſurie, and priuie expecting of ſome reward. That is done without the feare of God, and therefore it is harder for to obteine pardon, and neadeth the greater penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: this is done with remorſe of conſcience, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may the more eaſely be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuen, if vpon better information the grace of God be called for, who would all men to come to the knowledge of the truth, and ſo by his mercie and Sacramentes to come to ſaluation.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But you wil ſay perhaps, that ſome men ſette out their monie to
<pb facs="tcp:5452:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vſurie, to th'end they may be able to do good dedes with that gayne with ariſeth to them by vſurie. But as wel might he ſay, that he would robbe one man, to geue almoſe to another. For to ſuch the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Euil thinges are not to be don, that good things may follow thereon.</hi> God in dede vſeth to turne euil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good. But that is able to be don of him only, who can of nothing make ſomewhat. For an euil thing in that reſpect as it is euil, is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al, but is only a defect and fayli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſom goodnes or other. But ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who is not able to turne nothing into ſomewhat, or euil into good, may not preſume to do euil vpon hope of a good thing to follow, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens it is Gods only choiſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any good ſhal follow thereof, or no. And who ſo preſumeth that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his euil fact God wil work a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5452:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
good effect, he preſumeth of God.</p>
               <p>And leaſt I might ſeeme to write ſo weighty a matter vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my own head:<note place="margin">In Decres. <hi>14.</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi> c. ſi quis.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> ſaith without any exception: <hi>Si quis vſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accipit, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facit, vita no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viuit.</hi> If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue vſurie, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth violent robberie, he lyueth not euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly. And <hi>S. Augustine</hi> ſaieth, <hi>Nolite eleemoſynas facere de foenore &amp; vſuris, (&amp; pòſt) Dona iniquorum no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> probat Altiſsimus.</hi> Be ye not of the will to geue almoſe of that which is gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by multiplieng your ſtock, or by vſurie. The moſt high god alloweth not their giftes, who gette the goodes which thei geue vniuſtly. And <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Ep. 110.</note> 
                  <hi>That Almoſe pleaſeth God, which is geuen of goodes, rightly gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Thus we ſee, that it is not the geuing of almoſe which can make good the vſurers fault: but when he hath rendered
<pb facs="tcp:5452:15"/>
his owne to him whom he vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath oppreſſed, then lette him followe <hi>Zacheus,</hi> 
                  <q>in geuing away his owne goodes (and not other mens) vnto the poore.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Of geuing to lone or of lending, vvhich are naturally free contractes. The fourth Chapiter.</head>
               <p>THe firſt degree then of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines in any kinde of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal trafique appertaineth to almoſe deedes, as I ſhewed before, becauſe they come nigheſt to the great goodnes of God, who free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8</note> and without any recompenſe hoped for, gaue vs his owne ſonne, and al thinges beſide with him.</p>
               <p>The next degree of worthines after free giftes, belongeth to that liberal contract, which in Latin is called <hi>Mutuum,</hi> in Engliſh it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5452:15"/>
                  <hi>geuing to lone,</hi> or lending. The Latin name is compounded of two wordes, <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum</hi> myne, and thine, as if we might ſay in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Mynethine: whereby is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the thing which before was myne, is by lending made thine, to the end thou maiſt vſe it, being thine owne, and the value thereof muſt again of thine be made myne when it is reſtored back vnto me: ſo that geuing to lone for the time that it dureth, differreth not from a free gift, but is as much to ſay as a gift for ſo long, whereas a free gift is a gift for euer, without any reſtitution at al. But whiles the thing it ſelfe is in thy handes, it is not now mine, nor in it ſelf neuer ſhalbe, but I haue only a right to ſo much in quantitie, and to ſo good a thing in qualitie, as that was which I lent. In a free gift then I
<pb facs="tcp:5452:16"/>
can not aſke againe neither the thing it ſelfe, nor ſuch an other thing: but in lone, I may require ſuch an other thinge, but not the ſelf ſame which I lent.</p>
               <p>The better to vnderſtand this kind of bargain, it to be knowen, that there are two kindes of len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for whereas euerie lending is to thend the thing lent may be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of another man without my loſſe: the vſe of a thing may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two ſortes.</p>
               <p>And firſt to beginne with one, I may lend ſuch a thing as without alienating or periſhing maybe vſed of another man, as it chanceth when I lend him my howſe, my horſe, my plate or veſſel. He then that taketh my houſe to dwel in, may vſe my houſe this day, and again to morrow and ſo for many monethes or yeares together, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5452:16"/>
yet my howſe ſhall ſtill remaine vnperiſhed, although it may waſt more and more. And the like doth chance in my horſe, or any ſuch thinge as is not ſpent with the firſt vſe thereof. On the other ſyde, I may lend ſuch a thing as ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be imploied to his natural and proper vſe, except either the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of the ſame be alienated, or the thing it ſelfe doe periſh: for example, yf I lend you a barrel of beere, you can not vſe that beere to ſuche a purpoſe as beere is ordained vnto, except you drink it, or beſtow it where it may be drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is once drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yt ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be drunken no more, but it periſheth and ceaſeth to be any longer beere. The like is ſeene in corne, in oyle, in wine, and in ſuch other things as we vſe to number, weigh, or meaſure: the chief vſe
<pb facs="tcp:5452:17"/>
of all which is to be ſpent with the firſt vſe of them, and not to remaine ſtil his, whoſe they were before they were vſed.</p>
               <p>Whereas then ſome thinges may be vſed of him to whome they are lent, without ſpending of them, as howſes and horſes, but other thinges can not be vſed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be alienated and ſpent, as corne, and wine: theſe two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe vſes haue cauſed and made two diuerſe contractes and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines. For that contract where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the thinge dooth periſh toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the vſe, is called in latin <hi>Mutuum.</hi> The other wherein the thing lent remaineth ſtil in his vſe to whom it is lent, is called in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin <hi>Commodatum.</hi> In engliſh both contractes haue commonly one name, and are eche of them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Lone.</hi> But the natures of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5452:17"/>
thinges being diuerſe, do require a diuerſe handling of them, albeit both haue one name in our tonge, which may chance either thorow the barraines of the tonge, or ells thorow the ignorance of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, who vſe not to name that diuerſly, wherein they perceiue not an euident differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. But we may reaſonably engliſhe <hi>Mutuum,</hi> a geuing to lone: and <hi>Commodatum,</hi> a lending without any gift. For <hi>Mutuum</hi> is more then a lending, ſithens the thing is both geuen and lent: geuen from me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the proprietie, and lent to another concerning that I bind him to reſtore the like quantitie of the ſame kind of things. This firſt is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to both kindes of lending, that the thing lent, muſt be lent <hi>freely</hi> and without bargayning for any certaine hyer or wages. For if
<pb facs="tcp:5452:18"/>
I lend my horſe vpon a dayly pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is the contract of <hi>Locatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> or of ſetting out to hyer: and not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract of lending, or of geuing to lone whoſe nature is to be alwaies free and francke.</p>
               <p>The difference then betwene the two kindes of lending, is, that when I lend ſuch a thing as is not ſpent ordinarily with the firſt vſe, the thing lent remaineth ſtil mine owne. For when I lende my booke to my frind (whiche is a common thinge emong ſcholars) I doe not alienate the booke from me, but I remaine ſtill the lorde and proprietarie of it, lending my frind the vſe thereof. But when I geue to lone ſuch a thinge, as is ſtraight ſpent with the firſt vſe thereof: then not onely the vſe, but alſo the proprietie and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion thereof paſſeth from me to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5452:18"/>
him who boroweth yt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and good reaſon why. For al ſuch thinges are ſo principally made of God for one certaine vſe (as bread to be eaten, wine to be drunken) that the vſe differeth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thing it ſelfe. Becauſe they can not dure any longer when they are once vſed, but ſtraight doe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, and become either another thing, or at the leaſt another mans goodes.</p>
               <p>In conſideration whereof, he that lendeth me ſuche thinges, by the very lending, leeſeth the propriety and dominion of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ells I ſhould ſpend another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s goodes to his iniury, which is both againſt reaſon and alſo againſt his wil or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For as he would haue me take co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie of his goodes by vſing them: ſo would he not hinder him ſelf therewithal. But if
<pb facs="tcp:5452:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I ſhould borow a buſhel of wheat of another man, and yet the ſame buſhel of wheat ſhould ſtil be his, I ſhould either not vſe the wheat at al in making bread thereof, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieng it otherwiſe (and then it doth me no ſeruice) or els I ſhould ſpend yt being his, and thereby he ſhould ſuſtaine farther loſſe, then himſelfe would agree vnto. For if I do ſpend another mans goodes by his conſent, I am not anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him for them: no more then I ſhould anſwer him his oyle againe, who ſhould bid me throw it into the fyer.</p>
               <p>So that if he that boroweth corne, ſhould not ſtraight become lord and maiſter of the corne, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould neuer ſpend yt (and then yt ſerueth him not) or he ſhould ſpend yt with the lordes owne conſent, and then he were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5452:19"/>
bound to reſtore nothing at al, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented wittingly to the ſpending of his own corne. Which if it were ſo, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would euer lend ſuch thinges as be ſpent with the firſt vſe of them, except he were diſpoſed to geue them away. And ſeeing fewe men are prone to geue much, many poore men ſhould periſh for lacke of ſuſtenance.</p>
               <p>God therefore hath more ſweetely prouided, that in ſuche thinges as are ſpent and alienated from vs when we once vſe them, the dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and propriety ſhould be in the borower and ſpender of them, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he might boldly ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his own<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet he ſhould be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to reſtore ſo much again in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, or weight, or meaſure, as thei came vnto. Whereby the lender and alſo the borower is wel prouided for.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Herevpon yt inſueth, that who ſo boroweth thoſe thinges which are geuen to lone, and are ſpent with the firſt vſe, muſt beare all maner of peril<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bicauſe euery thing is alway at the loſſe of him, who is lorde and maiſter thereof.</p>
               <p>If then you borowe of me a pype of wine, and immediatly the wine be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from you by theues, or be otherwiſe loſt: I am not bound to beare any of the loſſe, but he only that boroweth it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is his wine, and not myne. But it is otherwiſe when I lend my horſe to a man. For if the horſe periſh, without any maner of his fault who borowed it: I looſe the horſe, and not he (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome expreſſe couenant be made to the contrarie) becauſe the horſe tarrieth ſtill myne, and was not his at al. Wherevpon Iuſtinian
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5452:20"/>
ſaith: <hi>Qui mutuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accepit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtitut. Quib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> des re co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabitur obligatio.</note> 
                  <hi>ſi quolibet fortuito caſu amiſerit quod accepit, veluti incendio, ruina, naufragio, aut latronum hostiúmue incurſu, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilominus obligatus remanet. At is qui vtendum accepit, ſanè quidem exactam diligentiam cuſtodiendae rei praeſtare iubetur: ſed propter maiore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vim, maioreſue caſus non tenetur, ſi modò non ipſius culpa is caſus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenerit.</hi> He that hath taken to lone, if he ſhal loſe that which he tooke, by whatſoeuer caſualtie or chaunce, as by fyre, by falling, by ſhipwracke, or by incurſion of theues or of enemies, he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth neuertheleſſe bound. But he that toke a thing to vſe, he is in dede co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to vſe exact dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in keeping yt: but he is not bound againſt greater force or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance then he is able to reſiſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſame hapned by his owne
<pb facs="tcp:5452:21"/>
default. This verely is the lawe of nature, and the rule of reaſon, that euerie thing ſhould be at his peril, who is the lord and owner of yt, except ſome other mans fault or ſome expreſſe couenant come betwene.</p>
               <p>Theſe thinges being ſo, it is to be knowen, that al coyne and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, whether it be of gold, of ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, of braſſe, or of leather, is to be reputed and numbred emong ſuch thinges as are ſpent with the firſt proper vſe of them. For monie is not like a booke, or a horſe, which being vſed to day, may be vſed againe of the ſame man to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and ſo one day after another: but monie is like to wheat, and to wine which as ſoone as it is vſed to that end whervnto it was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordained, is ſpent and alienated from him that borowed it. For if I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5452:21"/>
borowe tenne poundes of monie, I can not vſe thoſe tenne poundes (in ſpending them, ſo as monie is commonly vſed) except I geue yt, pay it out, or bye ſomewhat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And in al thoſe caſes the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie goeth from my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, ſo that I haue no more power vpon it: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I vſe it agayne, as vpon the former lone, except I come by it againe by a newe bargaine.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe al the lawiers and Philoſophers, aſwell thoſe that were before Chriſt, as thoſe that were after, and likewiſe all the Chriſtian Doctours, Biſhopes, and learned men haue with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord rekoned al mony and coyne, yea al mettalles which ſerue to bie or to paie withall, emong thoſe things which are ſpent when they are firſt vſed. Theſe are the wordes of Iuſtinian th'Emperour:
<pb facs="tcp:5452:22"/>
                  <hi>Mutui datio in ijs rebus conſiſtit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtitut. ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>quae pondere, numero, menſuráue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: veluti, vino, oleo frumento, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunia numerata, aere, argento, auro, quas res aut numerando, aut metien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, aut appendendo in hoc damus, vt accipientium fiant.</hi> Geuing to lone doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in thoſe thinges, which ſtand by weight, number, or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as in wine, oyle, corne, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered mony, braſſe, ſyluer, gold, which thinges we geue either by nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring, by meaſuri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, or by weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for this purpoſe, that they may be made theirs, who receiue them.</p>
               <p>Here we haue not only a plain authority, that mony is one of the things which is geuen to lone: but alſo we haue a reaſon ioyned ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. For if al things that conſiſt in meaſure or weight, or number, be of thoſe thinges which are geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lone: ſeing it is euident, that mony
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5452:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
may be both weighed and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered, yea ſometymes alſo meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: it is clere, that mony is emong thoſe thinges, which being geuen to lone, are ſpent with the firſt vſe, and not emong thoſe, which being lent, do ſtil remaine ſafe with him who vſeth them. Now the reaſon why geuing to lone doth conſiſt in ſuch thinges as are weighed, nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered, or meaſured, is, for that thoſe thinges, which can not be them ſelues reſtored againe to the former lord and maiſter of them, ought to be brought to an exact certainty, to th'end it may be eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently knowen, what he oweth who boroweth them. For no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would, that he who lendeth me his goodes freely ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by take any loſſe. Verely an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act certaintie is knowen by num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, meaſuring, and weighing.
<pb facs="tcp:5452:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
For theſe tryals neuer faile. If then I lend a quart of old french wine, although I can not aſke the ſelfe ſame quart againe: yet the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a quart maketh it certaine, how much he muſt paye who bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth the wine of me. And he muſt paye not only a quart, but a quart of that kind of wine, and of that goodnes whereof it was.</p>
               <p>Hytherto we haue learned, firſt, that geuing to lone is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract in nature next vnto almoſe deedes, or to a free gift, not diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at al from it, for the tyme that it dureth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that yt ought all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be free: otherwiſe it is no lone at al, but a ſelling or ſetting to hyer.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that yt differeth from ſimple lending, becauſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of the thing geuen to lone,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5452:23"/>
becometh his owne who borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth yt, which is not ſo in ſimple lending.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it inſueth herevpon, that in geuing to lone, the danger and loſſe is his only who borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and not at al his who geueth to lone: becauſe the lord of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing alwaies beareth the loſſe, and not he who had nothing to do withal.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, thinges geuen to lone be ſuch as conſiſt of weight, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and meaſure: as wine, oyle, corne or graine.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, monie is of thoſe thinges which are geuen to lone, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently he is not lord of yt who lent yt, but he only who boroweth it. And therefore if the mony lent, be ſtolen, or doe periſh by what ſoeuer miſchance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any default in the world of
<pb facs="tcp:5452:24"/>
him who doth borowe yt: yet he that gaue it to lone, may with ſafe conſcience aſke ſo much again as he lent, and the borower (if he be able) is bound to repaie yt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Hovv much it importeth, that the boundes and limites of euerie contract belonging to the lavv of nations, ſhould be inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably kept and maintayned. The v. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>WHereas al good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt lawes ought to be duly kept and obeyed, as by which the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale doth chiefly ſtand: yet ſpecially thoſe lawes are aboue al other to be eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry where mayntayned, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not only to particular cyties or ſtates, but euen to the whole ſocietie of all nations, and to the vniuerſall felowſhip of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5452:24"/>
For as the particular lawe is made vpon the particular reaſon and conſent of ſome one people: ſo the generall ordinances of all countries are made, vpon the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reaſon and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of al men in the whole world.</p>
               <p>Any one people may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes either blinded with affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or deceaued for lacke of good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And therefore their law being ſometime vniuſt, may in that caſe be iuſtly neglected. But that which pleaſeth al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of al ſtudies, educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſortes, can not ſuerly be erroneouſe or wrongfull, ſithens the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cometh only of God, who is the maker and gouernour of al. And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that wherein all men agree, muſt needes be ſuche a thing, as either nature it ſelfe taught them
<pb facs="tcp:5452:25"/>
al, or els great neceſsitie, publike profit, and long experience forced al men to agree vpon. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore who ſo breaketh that general decree and law of al nations, he is an enemie to the peace of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and is vnworthie to lyue in any part of that felowſhip, whoſe vnitie, concord and conſent he goeth about to ſette at diuiſion, diſcord, and variance. He is proud, ſeditiouſe, fooliſh, vnkind, and to ſaye all in one woorde, vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
               <p>If no man ſhal at al haue to doe with another, then is there battell byd to God him ſelfe, who made man in ſuch ſort, that he ſhould be cumpanable and inclined to lyue in ſocietie with other of his owne kind. And ſeeing ſo many kindes of byrdes and beaſtes kepe companie together accordingly as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5452:25"/>
their nature prouoketh them: ſhal only man, who is made lord ouer them all, be yet behind them all in this condition? To what purpoſe ſeemeth the gift of our ſpeache, if we ſhould not lyue with them who may heare and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vs? But if one man muſt and ſhal kepe companie with another, is yt not reaſon, that ſuch order be taken in common for all, that euerie one may without iniurie to him ſelfe, or to his neighbour, prouide for him ſelfe, and followe that voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein he is called?</p>
               <p>And whereas euerie countrie hath not euerie thinge, but one countrie hath that which another lacketh: nature, reaſon, experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon profit hath cauſed ſuch orders generally to be agreed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that euerie man of what ſoeuer nation or tong he be, may bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb facs="tcp:5452:26"/>
or exchange his wares with another in ſuch ſort, that althinges ſhalbe done to eche parties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, without loſſe or iniury to either of both. For ſeeing euerie man for his part is a member of the whole felowſhip of mankind, he muſt ſo keepe his owne place in the bodie where he liueth, that he neither put an other out of his roome, nor fayle to ſupplie his owne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that al things muſt be don in ſuch ſort to our neighbours, as we would haue them to do tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Which rule of nature is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> true, ſo neceſſarie, and ſo profitable to al men, that when Chriſt gaue to his diſciples the preceptes not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this mortal and tranſitory life, but alſo of life euerlaſting, yet he ſaied vnto them: <hi>Prout vultis vt faciant vobis homines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; vos facite
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5452:26"/>
illis ſimiliter.</hi> Euen as you would that men ſhould doe vnto you, do ye alſo lykewiſe towardes them. And S. Paule teacheth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 4</note> that <hi>if any man deceaue his brother in any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, God will reuenge yt.</hi> In ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that yt were better not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuffer hurt and wrong then to do yt: but alſo when he hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered it, rather to forgeue yt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> then to purſue the iniurie in open court and iudgement. How be it this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter point in dede is of counſel and perfection: but, not to doe any wrong to an other, yt is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, whiche of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie muſte be kepte and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Neither is yt harde to knowe, by what meanes we may avoyde to doo wronge, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as all manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes and bargaynes, that can chaunce in mans lyfe, haue bene
<pb facs="tcp:5452:27"/>
ſo exactly debated, limited and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed certayne thowſande yeares paſt according to naturall reaſon: that whereas there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kindes of couenantes and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynes, no one of them al can be broken by men, but they ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, that they do therein againſt the iudgement of reaſon, and ſo their owne conſcience ought to controll their deede. And he is not worthie to be named a man, who hauing the gift of reaſon, wil behaue him ſelfe as if he were a beaſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</note> Or why is it accompted of our <hi>Sauiour Christ</hi> ſo great a fault, <hi>without cauſe to call our broother foole:</hi> but becauſe in deede it is a great fault if any man play the foole, or doth become as though he were not partaker of witte and reaſon?</p>
               <p>For as yt is a great reproch and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5452:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſlander to cal him traytour, who is not knowen ſo to be: and as the reproche is ſo great, becauſe the fault of treaſon is moſt great: euen ſo is it a great reproche for a man indued with reaſon, to be called a foole, becauſe it is a great fault in him to do otherwiſe then reaſon would haue him do. For when S. Paule called the Galatians <hi>fooliſh:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</note> did he not then ſignifie, that they were extremely to be blamed for their groſſe vnderſtandinge and opinion.</p>
               <p>He that cometh to bargayne with another man, either he hath a good intent, or an euil. If it be euil, he is rather malitiouſe; then fooliſhe: if yt be good, ſeeing the kyndes of bargayning are knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let him vſe ſome one of them. He may lawfully bye or ſel, lend or borrowe, ſette or take to hyer,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:28"/>
trafique in merchandiſe, or ioyne in felowſhip, as he thinketh beſt for him ſelfe. But if he wil after fiue thowſand yeares wherein the world hath ſtoode, and hath by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent ordered and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed al couenants which belong to mans lyfe: If nowe he will vpon his own hed deuiſe a new kind of bargaine, or els wil change the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer nature of the old bargaynes: doubtleſſe (whether yt be for lacke of wytte, or of vertue) he is no meete man to lyue in any common weale, or to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſocietie of reaſonable men.</p>
               <p>My talke goeth to this purpoſe, that the vſurer may vnderſtand, the firſt point of his iniuſtice to be, in that he vſeth a contracte vnknowen to mankind, ſuche as breaketh many other contractes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5452:28"/>
and is a monſterouſe deuiſe, more lyke to an Idol, that is, to an idle imagination of his owne coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſe hart, then to any kind of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that men haue hitherto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, as yt ſhal more playnly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that whiche foloweth. And ſurely when <hi>S. Paule</hi> doth cal <hi>couetouſnes the bondage or ſeruitude of Idols,</hi> he there paynteth out no man ſo much, as he doth the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, to whom moſt properly that name doth belong, for many cauſes which ſhal appeare by that tyme this diſcourſe be ended.</p>
               <p>In the meane ſeaſon if I proue the vſurer to breake the contract of geuing to lone, which yet he doth and neceſſarily muſt vſe: I doubt not but any reaſonable man wil confeſſe, that he doth againſt the law of nations, which aſsigned certaine limites and bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to that
<pb facs="tcp:5452:29"/>
contract. And conſequently that he is a great offender: as who doth iniurie to his neighbour, and doth not kepe the rule of reaſon which God gaue, as to this ende, that we ſhould lyue togethers, as yt becometh reaſonable creatures to lyue. And ſurely he that brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſweete and gentill ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of God: ſhall be ſure in th'end to be brought vnder the rule of his ſeuere righteouſnes, and iudgementes, for that before he refuſed to lyue vnder his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo he that would not do to another that which he would wiſhe to be done vnto him ſelfe: ſhall ſuffer in him ſelfe iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that, which he vniuſtly layed vpon another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5452:29"/>
               <head>That the vſurer in ſetting out his mony for gayne, doth, and can not but geue his monie to lone. The vi. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>IT may be, that ſome man rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this my declaration of the nature of geuing to lone, will graunt in dede, that if the vſurer inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to geue his monie to lone, he did amyſſe. But (ſaith he) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes the vſurer is not of the mynde, to geue his money to lone: but to make ſome other kinde of bargayne. For he is not bound, when he doth geue out his mony, only to intend to geue his monie to lone: ſeeing there are other kyndes of bargayning made by conſent of both parties, ſome of the which the vſurer may and doth imbrace.</p>
               <p>To anſwer this obiection, it is
<pb facs="tcp:5452:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
nedeful to ſhew, how the vſurer, (wil he, nil he) only myndeth and doth geue his mony to lone. And yet ſeeing he breaketh the whole nature a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d euery poynt belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to lone, it wil follow thereof, that he muſt and doth vſe that contract of natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which yet he doth not kepe in any poynt, but vtterly breaketh and abuſeth the ſame. To geue to lone by the law of al people and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries is, to delyuer preſently to another man ſuch ſtuffe as is ſpent with the firſt natural and proper vſe therof, with bond to haue him repay ſo much and ſo good againe of the ſame kind. Thus the Grekes, the Latins, the Iewes, the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, the Lawyers, the Diuines, and generally al the heathens and Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s take to be the nature and true definition or deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to lone. Now the vſurer deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5452:30"/>
his mony or corne preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to another man, the proper vſe of the which mony, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the natural vſe of the which corne, is, to be ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and alienated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the borower when ſoeuer he vſeth them. And the borower is bound to repay the ſtock againe, to wit, the mony and the corn, as good, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as much as he receiued. Therfore the vſurer doth and muſt nedes vſe the contract of geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to lone. For his very fact and dede neceſſarily importes ſomuch. And if we go by name through al the other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tractes that euer haue ben deuiſed emong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: it ſhal wel appere, that the ſaid fact of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be no other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, but only the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract of geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to lone. If it were any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract in al the world, it ſhould be the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract of putting out to hyer. For it ſeemeth that the vſer would
<pb facs="tcp:5452:31"/>
ſet out his monie to hyer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to moneth, or yeare to yeare, as ſome men do their horſes from day to day. But the vſurers deede can not be that contract. For in putting out to hyer, the thinge which is ſet foorth, remaineth his owne, and he onely is lorde and owner thereof who ſetteth it out: and the ſelfe ſame ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which was deliuered, is reſtored againe to him without any change: As, he is lord and owner of the horſe who ſetteth out his horſe to hyer. For he letteth out only the vſe of his horſe to another man, reſeruing the proprietie and lordſhip to him ſelfe, and the very ſame horſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to him againe.</p>
               <p>But nowe when monie is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to be vſed of an other man, it is not poſsible that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerer ſhould remaine ſtill lorde
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5452:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and owner of the ſaid ſelfe monie, in ſuch ſorte that the borrower ſhould reſtore thoſe verie peces which he had taken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for then he ſhould not vſe the monie at all: ſeing that by vſing yt, he changeth yt, and putteth yt away from him: ſo that he can not haue the ſame monie againe to reſtore yt to the firſt delyuerer therof. Wherefore when mony is deliuered to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yt can not poſsibly be the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of ſetting to hyer.</p>
               <p>Moreouer the vſurer is not of this mynd him ſelfe, to haue the mony tarrie his owne ſtil. For then the daunger of leeſing yt ſhould be his alſo. But nowe yt is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ground of vſurie, in that men wil not haſard at al their principal ſomme of monie (otherwiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce they might haue more gaine, and that lawfully to, in the
<pb facs="tcp:5452:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
trade of merchandiſe, either by them ſelues alone, or in felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together with others. But whiles they will by all meanes be ſure of their principall, and will aduenture nothing: they are dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of this mynde, not to haue it periſh to their loſſe. If they will not haue it periſh from them, they muſt nedes haue it made his owne monie, who boroweth it, and to haue him dettor, not of the very ſelf ſame againe, but of ſo much in quantitie. For whiles the hundred poundes which I lend, is his to whom I lend it, and whiles he oweth me not the ſelfe ſame hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred poundes, nor any one thing that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be pointed to, but another hundred in a general ſomme: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by my hundred pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des are ſtil ſafe, and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer periſh. For no general quantitie doth euer periſh, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5452:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the particular thinges with are within ſome certaine place or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance. If then aboue al other things the lender wilbe ſure of his pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipal: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently his chief wil and intent is neceſſarily to alienate the principal ſomme from him ſelf, and to bring it to a general dette of a like ſomme in what ſo euer other mony or thing. So that come what chance ſhall to the borower, the hundred poundes lent, may not periſh, becauſe they are limited no where, and thereby they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect neither to fyre, nor to water, nor to enemies, nor to theues.</p>
               <p>If then the lender wil haue his principal ſafe in al euent, and yet it can not certainly be ſafe, except it be of a particular thinge made a generall dette: yt muſte needes be, that the lender deſyreth to haue his monie to be transferred
<pb facs="tcp:5452:33"/>
and alienated from him ſelfe, and to be made his who boroweth it, to thend al the loſſe that ſhal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, may come to the borower, and not to the lender. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, he that boroweth my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, doth not vſe nowe my monie, but his owne: for the mony which is myne, is a general ſome of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred poundes and not that which I deliuered. Otherwiſe yf it ſelfe tarie myne: as I may chalenge my owne horſe or coate, wherſoeuer I find it: ſo might I chalenge my owne hundered poundes. And then though it had paſſed thorow a hundered mens handes, I might claime it of him who preſently had it in poſſeſsion, which is ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſe to imagine: not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I can not knowe my owne mony from other mens, but albeit I had a coine by my ſelfe (al which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5452:33"/>
had bene only lent by me, and had bene none otherwaies alienated) yet al trafique would be muche hindred, or cleane taken away, if he that ſelleth his wares with a good conſcience for ready mony, ſhould be a feard, leaſt he that lent the mony to the byer, might laye handes on it agayne, whileſt it were in the ſellers poſſeſsion.</p>
               <p>By all theſe reaſons it plainly appeareth, that both the vſurer would haue his mony to be made his own who boroweth it, and yet if he would wiſh it otherwiſe, the verie deede and the nature of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract importeth ſo much, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the contract of ſetting out to hyer he ſtil remaineth lord of the thing, who doth ſet it out. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vſurer doth not, nor can not ſet out his mony to hyer, but he only doth geue it to lone.
<pb facs="tcp:5452:34"/>
Moreouer that which is ſet out to hier, is vſed a long time together, as a houſe for many yeres, a horſe for manie dayes. But the vſe of mony dureth no longer, then whiles it is a deliuering to another man. That which is ſet to hyer bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth either fruit to the borower, as lands do, or ſeruice, as houſes do: but mony ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for nothing, but to be ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and that ſeruice it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do but once. That which is ſet forth to hyer, cometh home moſt times the worſe for the wering: but mony is not the worſe to the geuer out therof, becauſe it hath the ſame weight and number and valew whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is repaied, which it had when it was deliuered. For al which cauſes mony ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ſet out to hier, but only is payd as det, or geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in almoſe, or geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, or geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lone, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it is properly vſed, it is made
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5452:34"/>
his, to whome it is deliuered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Hovv heynouſe, and hovv much againſt the nature of geuing to lone, and againſt the lavv of al Nations the vice of vſurie is. The vij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>THat the Reader may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inform himſelf co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the whole ſtate of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I wil firſt ſet foorth ſeuerally, what belongeth to the contract of lending, and afterward I wil ſhew, howe vſury doth breake all thoſe poyntes which were prouided by God, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind.</p>
               <p>Firſt of al by an vſurer I meane him, who bargaineth or greedily expecteth for ſome aduantage to aryſe aboue the principall corne, wine, or mony which he did lend. This much preſuppoſed, I ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of geuing to lone is, that it muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent deliuery of that which is lent:
<pb facs="tcp:5452:35"/>
otherwiſe if the thing be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered, it may be a promiſe of lending, but a lending it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The thing mutuated or geuen to lone muſt needes be made his owne, who boroweth yt: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe yt may wel be accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that is, the vſe of it may be only lent, but the thing it ſelfe is not geuen to lone, except it be made his who boroweth it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The thing geuen to lone muſt be made his freely who borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it: otherwiſe it ſhould rather be ſolde or ſet to hyer, then geuen to lone, if all that is done ſhould not be done without any reſpect of lucre.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> He that boroweth is not bound to reſtore the verie thing whiche he tooke, but only the value ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and that he is bound to doe in moſt preciſe maner, by number,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5452:35"/>
weight, or meaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> When monie is geuen to lone, the nature of it muſte be kepte, which is only to ſerue for excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge or price of all other thinges, and not to make a gaine of the penny yt ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Thinges are geuen to lone na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally for another mans ſake who boroweth yt, and not for his who lendeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Thinges geuen to lone, ſhould rather be geuen to lone to the pooreſt ſorte of men, then to the richeſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The contract of geuing to lone was inuented for the benefite of common weales, that whileſt he that had the thing, did lend it to an other who had it not, by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes frindſhip might be maintained, and the richeſſe of one might eaſe the lacke of another.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:36"/>Nowe I ſay: all theſe former pointes of natural honeſty and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie are broken, or at the leaſt defaced by the vſurer, be the vſury which he taketh, or which he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for, neuer ſo ſmal.</p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt point of al, it is proued before, that euerie vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is neceſſarily a geuer to lone: and therefore he ſhould keepe the nature of geuing to lone: but he hath broken yt diuerſe wayes.</p>
               <p>It is throughly agreed vppon betwene al men, that he who bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth tenne poundes of me, is bound to repay it againe. Let vs then conſider, how and why he is bound thereunto? Surely naturall reaſon ſheweth, that he is bound to repaie the tenne poundes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he tooke yt of me with this intent and condition of myne, that he ſhould reſtore as muche in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5452:36"/>
value agayne. But were not this intent of myne ioyned with the deliuerie of the monie it ſelfe, he were not bounde to repaye yt. For if yt were deliuered with this intent, to geue yt him, or ells that he ſhould onely carrie yt to another man: then he ſhould not be bound to repay it.</p>
               <p>Againe, if I deliuered not the tenne poundes, but onely inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to make an other man the dettor thereof, without, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it to him at all: lykewiſe no reaſon would, that he ſhould be bound vpon my onely intent, to pay that whiche he tooke not. Twoo thinges then muſt concurre to make the borower owe me tenne poundes: the deliuerie of the monie: and the intent to make him dettor of it. If any one of theſe two fayle, he is no dettor.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:37"/>Howe ſay we then in vſurie? Admitte that I deliuer ten poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vnto my neighbour with this intent, that he ſhall repaie the value of the ſame tenne poundes, and alſo tenne ſhillinges more by the yeare ſo long as he keepeth it: I ſay this intent of myne can not make him owe me the tenne ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges by the yeare. For the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of geuing to lone is a reall contract<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is to ſay, the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation thereof dependeth onely vpon the thing which is deliuered in the way of lone. Somuch then and no more is naturally owed, by the way of geuing to lone, as is delyuered from hand to hand. But the tenne ſhillinges whereof we ſpeake, was not at al deliuered to my neighbour: therefore he can not owe yt at al vpon the ground of taking my tenne poundes to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5452:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
lone. So that if I either take, or in my hart looke for the tenne ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges as my dette: I doe iniurie, and doe ſinne againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God, who forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me not only to ſteale, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>to couet an other mans goodes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If you ſay, that the other man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenteth to geue me the ſayd ten ſhillinges, and therefore that it is no iniurie to take yt: I anſwer, that he conſenteth not freely vnto yt, but as he doth, who geueth his purſe vnto a theefe vpon the high way for feare of a worſe turne. For the borower is only therefore content to geue the tenne ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges aboue the principall dette, becauſe the naughtie maners of men haue now brought matters to paſſe in ſuche ſorte, that without payeng the vſurie, he ſhould not haue had the mony. But if euerie
<pb facs="tcp:5452:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thing were as it ought to be: that is, if geuing to lone were alwaies free as it ſhould be, then ſhould no vſurer require, neither any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant cuſtomably offer, a yearely rent for the lone of monie. But now although the borower ſeeme willing to pay it, and therefore is thought to haue no iniurie: yet in deede he payeth it no more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, then he that is in a tempeſt, doth willingly caſt out his goodes into the ſea: that is to ſay, he choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to pay it, becauſe it would be worſe with him, if he payd it not. For he feareth, that otherwiſe the monie ſhould be taken out of his handes. And as the theſe, to whom for ſafegard of my life, I delyuer my purſe, hath yet no right vnto my monie, but wrongfully with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth that which is not his: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo the vſurer that extorteth a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5452:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
yearely rent of the monie, doth therein vniuſtly, and is bound in conſcience to reſtore it againe: except the borower without all colour or cloaking doo franckely and freely geue it him, whiche ſurely in this reſpect is ſeldome to be ſeene.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Christ came into the world to vndoe the workes of the deuill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note> and to ſette men againe at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that al falſe pretenſes (of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing rewardes for monie borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) being taken away: he that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth may in dede haue the vſe of the mony ſo freely, as God and natural reaſon hath ordained yt ſhould be. Whervpon Chriſt ſayd <hi>Date mutuum nihil inde ſperantes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.</note> Geue ye to lone, hoapi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thereof: that is to ſay, of,<note place="margin">In Pſalm. <hi>36.</hi> Concio. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> or aboue the lone. And in that meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin ſaith: <hi>Si foener aueris hoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, id eſt,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:39"/>
mutuam pecuniam tuam dederis, à quo aliquid plus quàm dedisti expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes accipere: no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pecuniam ſolam, ſed aliquid plus quàm dedisti, ſiue illud triticum ſit, ſiue vinum, ſiue oleum, ſiue quodlibet aliud, ſi plus quàm de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disti expectas accipere: foenerator es, &amp; in hoc improbandus, non lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandus.</hi> If thou ſette foorth thy goodes for vſurie, that is to ſaie, if thou geue him thy monie to lone, of whome thou lookeſt to receaue anie thinge more then thow gaueſt, I ſaie not onelie mony, but any thinge more then thow gaueſt, whether that be wheat, or wine, or oyle, or what ſoeuer thing els: if thow lookeſt to receaue more then thow ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, thow art an vſurer, and in that behalfe thow art to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and not to be praiſed. This much concerning the firſt point
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5452:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of geuing to lone, which was, that by the nature of that contract no more could be owghed, then was geuen and deliuered by him that did geue to lone.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d point of geuing to lone, it hath bene ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proued, that the thing ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to lone, though it be monie, muſt be made his owne goodes, who boroweth it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower is lorde of the monie the ſelfe ſame hower wherein it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto him by the way of lone. And how I pray you then can vſurie poſsibly ſtand with this point? Is it reaſon that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould pay for the vſe of that whiche is throughly his owne. They are deceaued who thinke, that the borower doth vſe their monie. He doth not ſo. For the mony is made his owne by the very acte of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing
<pb facs="tcp:5452:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it: and he paieth right wel for it, in as muche as he taketh it vpon his own aduenture, and bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him ſelfe generally to repay ſo much, whatſoeuer becometh of the particular monie which he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</p>
               <p>If then the monie which is vſed be not mine, but only a lyke gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſumme is owing to me in the ſtead thereof (as it was ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) why ſhuld the borower pay me for the vſe of that, which now belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth not vnto me? The ſumme which he oweth vnto me, is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: the ſumm which he occupieth is particular. If he pay vſurie for the general ſumme which is mine: it is iniurie, becauſe he doth not occupie it. If he pay vſurie for the particular ſumme which he occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieth: it is alſo iniurie, for that ſumme he oweth not.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:5452:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>Therefore if in right and truth we wil make any man dettor vnto vs for the vſe of our mony, we muſt prouide, that the mony doo tarrie ſtil ours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is to ſay, we muſt let the merchant occupie yt as our baylie or factor: and ſo if it be loſt, to beare the loſſe: and if yt be ſaued, to partake of the gayne. But as that is farre from the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers purpoſe: ſo is it farre out of the way, that the merchant who occupieth not the vſurers monie, but his owne, ſhould yet reward the vſurer for that which is nowe no more his. Againe, admitte the mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t did vſe the vſurers mony: yet no reaſon would beare, that he ſhould paie a yerely rent for that, which being once vſed, is for euer alienated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. If the borower alienate but a peece of the monie which he toke, he vſeth but a pece.
<pb facs="tcp:5452:41"/>
If he vſe it all, he doth alienate all. If then he pay rent for the monie before the alienation thereof, he paieth rent for it, before he doth vſe it. If he pay rent after the alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, he paieth rent for it after that it is out of his vſe. If he pay rent for the tyme whiles he is a vſing of it, ſeeing that is no longer then whiles he is a deliuering of it: by what iuſtice ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a yerely rent be due for a fact which dureth but a ſmal moment? Thus in al caſes it is vtterly vniuſt, to pay any rent or penſion for mony, or any other like thinge whiche was taken to lone.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, whereas al geuing to lone ought to be free, ſeeing the vſurer is neceſſarily prooued to geue his mony to lone, and yet his geuing is not free: no excuſe can be brought, but that the vſurer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5452:41"/>
breaketh this point alſo. And yet this point of al other pleaſeth God moſt, in ſo much that Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted men to this contract, <hi>bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them geue to lone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for any thing thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We reade not ſurely, that Chriſt exhorted men to by and to ſell, or to follow the trade of merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. For he knew right wel, that al men are readie inough to make ſuch exchanges as ſeeme to be for their commoditie. But becauſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to lone is a free and liberal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, wherevnto fewe men are prone: therefore as he exhorted vs to geue almoſe, euen ſo did he exhort vs to geue to lone.</p>
               <p>And the vaine glorious man of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth God moſt greuouſly, who pretending to geue almoſe, doth in deede rather bye vaine glorie with his pennie dole, then exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb facs="tcp:5452:42"/>
anie charitable act: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doth he much more greuouſly offend God, who pretending to geue to lone, doth rather ſel then geue his mony, there ſeeking for moſt filthy lucre, where euen the heathens confeſſed no lucre could haue place, as I ſhewed before out of the ciuil lawe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth point of geuing to lone, is, that the borower is bound to reſtore that which he tooke, in moſt preciſe maner, to wit, by nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, weight, or meaſure. Howe doth the vſurer obſerue this point, when he taketh twelue for ten, three pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for two, and fiue buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhels of corne for ſo wer?</p>
               <p>It is notable to ſee, howe the goodnes of God hath defenced and warded the contracte of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to lone, as who foreſaw, that it being the beſt and higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5452:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of al next vnto almoſededes, yet ſhalbe of all other moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly abuſed.</p>
               <p>Al equality of excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges and the valew of al thinges is moſt exactly knowen by number, weight, and meaſure. And geuing to lone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth only of ſuch thinges as are numbered, weighed, and meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. So that no other contract is ſo certaine, and ſo preciſely boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or limited, as this of geuing to lone.</p>
               <p>Therefore the more ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and garde God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided to keepe aequalitie and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in this contracte, the more vniuſte and the greater breakers of Gods ordinaunces they are, who notwithſtanding require or hope for more in number, weight, or meaſure, then they did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:43"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Let vs nowe come to the fifth point, which belongeth peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to monie alone. Many other thinges may be geuen to lone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides monie, as wine, corne, oyle, with ſuch like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and vſurie may be committed, if more then was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be receaued in any of them. But when monie is geuen to lone (as in vſurie it cometh moſt tymes to paſſe) then is there a ſpecial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie alſo in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>Is to be knowen, that monie was inuented by the common co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of men, ſpecially to ſerue ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s neceſsitie and commoditie, in chopping and changing thinges to and fro.<note place="margin">Ariſtoteles in Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.</note> For in the beginning he that lacked any thinge, as for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample, a payer of ſhooes, he went to an other man that had ſhooes enough, and brought him ſuche ſtuffe wherof him ſelfe had ſtore,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5452:43"/>
as cloth perhaps, or ſkinnes, or ſome like matter to make an equal exchange betwene them both. So that thing for thing was exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: and that was the moſt ſimple and natural kinde of trafique be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene men. But experience decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that this way at length was incommodiouſe, and would not ſerue euerie mans turne. For ſome tymes he that had ſhooes which I lacked, had alſo cloth and ſkinnes aſwel as I, and then he was loth to take my cloth for his ſhooes, ſeeing that he had cloth enough of his owne. For which cauſe wiſe men deuiſed, that ſome certaine mettal ſhould ſerue the turne of al men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that who ſo needed any ſtuffe, he ſhould take ſuch a kind of metall or coyne (to witte, lead, or lether, and at the length braſſe) and for that he ſhould receaue of another
<pb facs="tcp:5452:44"/>
man whatſoeuer he neaded.</p>
               <p>Thus mettal was at the firſt eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by conſent, and deliuered by weight: ſo that a pound of braſſe ſhould be (for example) the price of a payer of ſhooes. And when it was found troubleſome alſo, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for them that went abrode, to carrie ſuch weight of mettal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, and to ſtand long in weighing it: in ſtead of a greate deale of braſſe, a litle ſyluer, and leſſe golde was at the length inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Yea then alſo it was farther deuiſed, that a certaine coyne or print ſhould be ſet vpon the ſyluer or golde: ſo that we ſhould not neede alwaies to weigh yt, but that the verie form ſhould ſtraight ſhew the value thereof.</p>
               <p>Monie then was made to ſerue all exchanges, and to be alone the price of al other thinges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5452:44"/>
it ought to be vſed none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, then that thing was v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in whoſe place yt came. But neuer was any couenant or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge made for this ende, that the thing whiche was throughly alienated, ſhould be increaſed to his aduantage, who did alienate the ſame. For either a man ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth away ſome of his goodes freely, and then nothing at all therof is due to him againe in this worlde: or els he chaungeth ſome of his goods for other thinges, and then the thing that he deliuereth what ſo euer cometh of it, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fruitful to him that receaueth it. But neuer was there yet ſuch a gift or ſuch an exchange heard of, wherein the thing which I deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of my lordſhip and propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, ſhould thereby render the more fruit or profit to me againe.
<pb facs="tcp:5452:45"/>
For that whereof men will take profitte, they vſe to keepe in their owne proprietie, and ſo either to vſe it them ſelues, or to ſette it out to be vſed for a penſion, and not to geue it or exchange it vtterly away from them.</p>
               <p>But the vſurer geueth away his monie to an other man, as it was proued before: and ſo doth it for this end, that his monie may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by bring him the more fruite and gaine. Whiche is vtterly againſt the end, for whiche either any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exchange, or mony it ſelf was made. For it was made to bring all thinges to an equallitie, and to be as it were a rule and meaſure, whereby the value of all other thinges might quickly be knowen and eaſely counterpeiſed. But now the vſurer maketh monie to ſerue for the greateſt inequalitie that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:5452:45"/>
be deuiſed of man. For where the borower did receaue but tenne, or ſome ſuche certaine number of crownes, he maketh him a dettor not onely of ſo many, but no man is able to tel of how many: ſithens if the borower pay but twoo crownes ouer by the yeare, in one hundered yeares he ſhall paie for tenne crownes twoo hundered crownes: and yet ſhall he ſtil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine dettor of the ten crownes, alſo. And al this is done of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer by thoſe tenne crownes which he did put away from him ſelf, and made them another mans. Was euer any ſuche thing heard of? that by making my goodes to be another mans, I ſhould thereby be the greater gayner: yea ſo farre greater, that the gaine ſhould be without al meaſure or ende? For thoſe tenne crownes may from
<pb facs="tcp:5452:46"/>
age to age be onely ſayd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the bancke (as in ſome places it chanceth) and ſo within a thowſand yeares they make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of two thouſand crownes.</p>
               <p>Adde herevnto, that in caſe the poore man, who borowed the ten crownes, do not pay his vſurie in ten yeres, he is then dettor of twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty crownes: of ten for the principal a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of other ten for the vſury, which the vſurer begetteth and engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth (as it were) to the intolerable loſſe of the borower, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsiue gayne of him ſelfe: and yet theſe ten crownes be not his own al this while, although he picke out ſo great aduantage of them. Yea al this while thei be no where at al. For in one moment they were conſumed and ſpent by him that borowed them, and in place of them an Idoll is conceaued,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5452:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
whiche Idoll doth remaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſely, not any where in nature and truth, but in name and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. For it is feyned, that the tenne crownes lye ſtill in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine bancke, and there do begette litle ones, whiche agayne haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther litle ones. And whereas all other thinges die and periſhe, and many beaſtes whiche nature made apte to increaſe, by caſualties prooue barren: yet theſe tenne crownes, whiche by nature were barren, and in truth are ſpent: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill ſo fruitefull in the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers vaine imagination, and in the borowers moſt greuouſe penſion, that if the world ſhould ſtand for euer, they alſo ſhould be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and ſhould neither die, nor euer become barren.</p>
               <p>See ye not this Idol, which the Deuill hath conſecrated in the
<pb facs="tcp:5452:47"/>
world? And he hath conſecrated yt againſt the nature of monie, which was inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for other vſes, and not at al for this.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Now foloweth the ſixt point. For whereas the contract of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to lone was altogether inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for his commoditie who bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth the thing (as being a kynd of gyfte for the tyme, and al giftes are inſtituted for the receauers te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie) yet the vſurer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to directe his geuing to lone wholie for his owne commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, and therefore he tarrieth not vntil the merchant come to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe his mony of him: but he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeketh out a merchant who may take his mony to vſury<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is an euident peruerting of Gods ordinance, not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the act of lending, but alſo concerning the end of the act.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:5452:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seuenthly, whereas geuing to lone was inſtituted for the reliefe of the poore, that he to whome I would not, nor was not able free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to geue my mony: yet that he might at the leaſt take commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by borowing the ſame: nowe the vſurer doth ouerthrowe this point alſo and ſeketh for the moſt ſubſtanciall merchant that he can heare of, as though it were an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſe to caſt water into the ſea, or to helpe forward the richeſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of all. And thus he abuſeth the perſons alſo, for whoſe ſake the contracte of geuing to lone was inſtituted of God.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, ſhall no man then lend any thing to him that is riche? I ſay not ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But a man may be rich in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>thing, and poore in another. A man may be riche in gold and ſylu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he may abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:5452:48"/>
in victuals, in wine, and beere: yet perhaps he is without a cup of ſmal ale, which the Phyſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith to be better for hym, then any other kind of drinke. If then I lend this riche man a quart of my ale, I lend it to him as needing it, and as being poore in that behalfe. But it were farre otherwiſe, if whereas he oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieth certain thowſand pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des by the yeare, I would offer him my forty or fifty poundes in the way of lone. For here, ſeing I offer that vnto him, which would ſerue to ſet vp another poore man, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I doo it not for his ſake, but for hoape of gaynes to my ſelf, as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting my ſtocke to be ſure in his hands, and looking for yerely rent thereof: in this caſe (which is the caſe of vſurers) it may wel appere, that my intention is only to reiſe gaines of that contract: and by ſuch
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5452:48"/>
a one, to whom of al other I ſhould leaſt haue lent my monie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> For the laſt point of al, it is to be noted, that not only he is naturally iniured, who for mony, wine, corn oyle, or any like thing, payeth the ouerplus: but alſo the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale is extremely da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maged therby. For the merchant, who taketh a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred poundes of me, payeng me by the yere, ten, or ſix poundes ouer the principal ſumme: is conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo to ſel his wares, that he may reiſe thoſe tenne or ſix poundes aboue his ordinarie gayne. So that in the length the poore man, who cometh to bye the ſayd wares by peecemeale, is burthened with his vſury, who had ſomuch idle mony, that he was able to ſet it out to hier to an other man. Now in caſe the merchant, who taketh the monie to lone, be not hable to reyſe that
<pb facs="tcp:5452:49"/>
gayne him ſelfe, which he geueth yerely to the vſurer for his monie: then by litle and litle he leeſeth his creditte, vntill at the laſt he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come playne <hi>Banckrupt,</hi> and ſo he not only leeſeth his principal who looketh for gayne: but alſo manie other men, who made lawful bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines with the ſayd merchant, are defrauded of their right and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made vnable to keepe towche with others, wherevpon ariſeth from man to man, an infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and loſſe both of credit and of goodes.</p>
               <p>Farthermore, how manie idle men doth vſurie cauſe to be in a realme? For whereas no gaines is either more eaſie then that which is gotten with another mans tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, or els more certaine then that which is without hazard of the principall (as at the leaſt men
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5452:49"/>
thinke) he that can gette once ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo meane a ſtocke of monie, maketh accompte to lyue vppon the fruites thereof, and ſo ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his tyme in ſportinge and playenge: whereas if the ſaied hoape of vſurie were taken from him, he ſhould be conſtrained to take ſome other trade of life, which might be more to his owne honeſtie, and to the profitte of the common weale.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, where vſurie is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed openly, there God muſte needes be offended, becauſe an vniuſt law contrarie to his worde and will, is ſuffered to preuayle. And conſequently as no priuate mans offence is leaft vnpuniſhed at Gods hande, ſo muſte the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, whiche permitteth ſo great an offence, looke alſo for a common puniſhment to fall vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5452:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
yt, ſithens God is infinitely iuſt, and letteth nothing growe ſo farre out of order, but that if it wil not abide vnder the order of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull gouernement, it ſhall fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the order of his ſeuere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: leaſt any thing that reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably ought to be done, might be left vndone by his infinite wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power.</p>
               <p>Thus haue wee ſeene ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie cauſes, whye vſurie is vniuſte: but none at all, why the lender may take any penſion for his lone. If you ſaye you lacked your monie a longe tyme: I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that in caſe you had any knowen and certayne loſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, which was not foreſeene of you when you lent yt, you may aſke the ſauinge of your ſelfe harmeleſſe: becauſe that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed from the beginninge,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5452:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that you woulde not geue out your mony to lone, to your owne hindrance. For as this contract of geuing to lone can abyde no gayne: ſo needeth it not to ſuſtaine any loſſe.</p>
               <p>But yf the monie would haue lyen idely by you al that tyme (as commonly it ſhould haue done, becauſe they are either riche, or ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wthfull, who geue to lone) then you do an iniurie vnto God, in ſelling the time whiche is none of yours. For if you wil haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges only becauſe your monie hath ben a yeare in another mans hand, wheras if it had bene in your own handes, it had bene eyther loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp in a cheſt, or ells commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſome haſard or peril: there is no cauſe why you ſhould aſke the ſayd wages or penſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but becauſe ſo much tyme hath paſſed ouer,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:51"/>
wherein he was your dettor, and the meaſure of the ſayd tyme was not of your gift vnto your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but of Gods gift vnto you both. For ſelling of the which, you are lyke to geue an accompt vnto God.</p>
               <p>Yea (but ſaye you) my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie had bene ſafer in myne owne coffer. I can not tell you that. For then a theefe might haue ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len yt, or fyer might haue conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it. But nowe it is put out of all perill in his handes, who ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a generall ſumme of ſo much in quantitie. Yea but perhappes he will not be able to repaye yt. If you thought ſo, you woulde not lend yt. For he that geueth his monie to vſurie, ſeeketh not the commoditie of the borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but onely, or principally, his owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:5452:51"/>Nowe yf in the end it chance, that the borower is not able to repay yt: that is not any excuſe to the vſurer, who can not aſke mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie for that caſualtie, whiche he might vtterly auoyde by not len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his monie at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or yf he wil needes lend his monie, he may either take ſuerties or pledges for the principall, without requie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any vſurie of the borower: for the more vſurie the borower payeth, the leſſe he is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay the principall, in ſo muche as he is made the poorer by pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng the vſurie. But yf he payed no vſurie at all, he ſhould be better able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay that whiche he firſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5452:52"/>
               <head>That the Heathens condemned vſurie, The viij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>BY the reaſons before named the verie Heathens were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and perſwaded, that vſurie was agaynſt nature, and conſequently that it was a fowle crime, and a great ſinne. In ſo much that the great Philoſopher <hi>Aristotel</hi> ſpeaketh thereof in this wiſe:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticorum.</note> 
                  <hi>Optimo iure laborat odio ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiatio foeneratorum, quia ab ipſo numo quaestum petit, non id pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter quod inuentus est, quippe qui gratia mutandi fuerat inductus. Etenim foenus auget numum, vnde etiam coepit hoc nomen. Similia por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò ſunt ea quae pariuntur gigne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus: in foenore numus paritur a numo. Quamobrem vel maximè praeter na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam eſt illa quaestus faciendi ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</hi> The trafique of vſurers is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5452:52"/>
worthely hated, becauſe it ſeketh gaynes vppon the pennie: and it ſeeketh not that for the which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie was inuented. For mony was inuented to make exchange with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: but vſurie (exchangeth not, but) increaſeth the pennie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of alſo it toke his name (in Greke) Now thoſe thinges which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, are lyke to them by which they are begotten. In vſurie mony bringeth foorth mony: wherefore that kind of gayning is ſpecially againſt nature.</p>
               <p>The verie ſame thing ſaith <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> in a Treatiſe whiche he wrote, exhorting men not to haue to do with vſurers: <hi>Quid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch. quod non oporteat foenerari.</note> 
                  <hi>quod foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratores naturalia quoque deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, quae aſſerunt, ex nihilo nil gigni poſſe: quandoquidem apud illos ex eo quod non est, neque vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam fuit, vſura generatur. (Et
<pb facs="tcp:5452:53"/>
pòſt:) Longè plus foeneratores in ſuis ephemeridibus imponunt, ſcribentes miſero illi tantum mutuaſſe, cum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men multò minus acceperit. Siqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mendacium cauſa lucri, non ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitate, neque ob indigentiam, ab il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis fieri ſolet, ſed propter inſatiabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.</hi> The vſurers do alſo mocke at thoſe rules of nature, whiche affirme, that of nothing, nothing can be begotten. But yet emong them, vſurie is begotten of that, whiche is not, nor neuer was. The vſurers put in much more in their counte bookes, writing that they haue lent ſuche a poore man this muche, whereas he yet hath taken much leſſe. For they vſe to lye for gaines ſake, not for neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, or poouertie (whiche were the leſſe euill) but for inſatiable greedineſſe.</p>
               <p>Thus are three great abuſes by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5452:53"/>
the wiſemen of the verie heathens reproued in vſurers. The firſt is, in that they againſt nature will make a barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thing (as monie is) to bring foorth as it were children, that is to ſay, pence and ſhillinges: and this fault is common to all v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers. But the other two are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed by extreme practiſes of vſurie. The formoſt is, in that they exacte vſury ſo long, that at the laſt the dettor payeth vſurie, not only for the principal ſumme, but alſo for the verie vſurie it ſelf. As thus: Lette him borowe one hundred pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, payeng after the rate of fower poundes in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie poundes euerie yeare for the vſurie. If the firſt yeare he myſſe to repay his twentie poundes for the hundred, the ſecond yeare he is dettor of ſix ſcore poundes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that yeare his vſurie is twentie
<pb facs="tcp:5452:54"/>
fower poundes: wherin he payeth fower poundes for the twentie which he neuer receaued, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly became dettor thereof by vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo euerie yeare after, if he omitte to paye the vſurie, he ſhall paye not only for the rate of the hundred poundes: but alſo as yf he had receaued al that, which he ceaſeth to pay. So that whereas in all vſurie a barren thing doth bring foorth: in this later kynde, that alſo doth bring foorth, which is not onely barren, but is nothing at al, nor neuer was in the natural truth of thinges.</p>
               <p>The thirde fault in great vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers is, when to avoyde the payne of the lawe, they colour the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo, that they write in the bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of debte, hym to haue bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of them a hundred poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, who had but fower ſcore.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5452:54"/>
When <hi>Cato</hi> the graue Senator of Roome conſidered theſe greate vices: he being aſked,<note place="margin">Cicero. <hi>2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Offic.</note> 
                  <hi>what yt was, to lende out monie vppon v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie:</hi> aunſwered, <hi>it is no better then to kill a man.</hi> The which ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his <hi>Tullie</hi> rehearſeth both for <hi>Catos</hi> prayſe, and in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe of vſurie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>That the Ciuil lavve doth not acknovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge vſurie to ſpring or ariſe of the nature of ſuche thinges as are geuen to lone, but rather to be contrarie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. The ix. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuche as ſome men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the defenſe of their vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by the Ciuil law, which thei ſay to be a ſure defender of the law of nature: yt is alſo requiſite,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:55"/>
that we declare, what the Ciuill law thinketh in this behalfe.</p>
               <p>Vſurie hath his name of vſing, and thereby is meant the price or eſtimation of the vſe of a thing. And becauſe we may vſe certaine thinges, the ſubſtance of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning ſafe, as when we hyer another mans ground, or dwell in an other mans houſe: in that caſe yt is lawefull to pay vſurie for the vſe of the ſayd houſe or landes. But when there is no vſe of a thing without the loſſe and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away thereof, or when the thing is diminiſhed in ſubſtance by the dayly vſing of yt: that is not properly <hi>Vſus,</hi> the vſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Cicero and Vlpian cal yt, <hi>Abuſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero in Topicis.</note> the abuſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as yf we ſhould ſaye in engliſh, it is rather a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, then an vſing.</p>
               <p>Thoſe thinges that may be vſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5452:55"/>
and yet remaine ſafe, may alſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yearely rentes or fruites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the lord of them may geue or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath the proprietie and ownor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of them to one, and the vſe and fruite or profite to an other. Which thing can not be done in thoſe goodes, whiche are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and ſpent by the vſe of them, becauſe the vſe doth diminiſh the ſubſtance yt ſelfe. Wherevpon <hi>Iustinian</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Inſtitut. de vſufruct. § Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit.</note> 
                  <hi>Constituitur vſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fructus in fundo, &amp; aedibus, &amp; caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris rebus, exceptis his quae ipſo vſu conſumuntur. Nam hae res neque na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali ratione, neque ciuili recipiunt vſumfructum, quo in numero ſunt vinum, oleum, frumentum, vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, quibus proxima est pecunia numerata<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> namque ipſo vſu aſsidua permutatione quodammodo extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitur. Ergo Senatus non fecit qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem earum rerum vſumfructum (nec
<pb facs="tcp:5452:56"/>
enim poterat) ſed per cautione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaſi vſumfructu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stituit.</hi> Vſe and fruite is aſsigned in landes, howſes, and other thinges, ſauing thoſe which are waſted with the verie vſe. For thoſe thinges receaue no vſe and fruite neither by naturall, nor by ciuil meanes: of the whiche ſorte wine, oyle, corne, and garmentes are, to whoſe nature nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bered (or, redie) monie approcheth next, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yt is in maner worne in the verie vſing of yt by continual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge. Therefore <hi>the Senate</hi> (of Rome which decreed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe matters) <hi>made not vſe and fruite of theſe thinges (for yt was not able ſo to do)</hi> but it aſsigned as it were after a ſort, how to vſe and to take profite of them with a prouiſo, that who had the vſe and fruite of any ſuch thinges left or geuen him, ſhould receaue the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5452:56"/>
thinges, and ſhould bynd him ſelfe to reſtore ſo much monie agayne at his death (if it were monie) or els the value of them, if they were wine, oyle, or corne.</p>
               <p>To our purpoſe it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the lawyers confeſſed theſe thinges not to haue proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any vſe and fruite, which might be ſeparated from their proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. In ſo much that it was not poſsible to aſsigne vſe and fruite vpon them: verely becauſe it was againſt nature ſo to do. And Caius ſaieth in this very caſe whereof we ſpeake:<note place="margin">In Pande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis de vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruct earu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rerum quae vſu conſu. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Senatuſconſulto non id effectum eſt, vt pecuniae vſusfructus proprius eſſet. Nec enim naturalis ratio authoritate Senatus commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri potuit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſed remedio introducto coepit quaſi vſusfructus haberi.</hi> It is not brought to paſſe by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Senate, that there be
<pb facs="tcp:5452:57"/>
a proper vſe and fruit of monie. <hi>For natural reaſon could not be cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the authoritie of the Senate.</hi> But a ſhift being found, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne as it were a certaine vſe and fruite of mony to be taken and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted.</p>
               <p>Thus, that which by witte of man might be deuiſed in a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly common weale, was done for profitte and commodities ſake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature it ſelfe. But that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe which th'Emperour ſpeaketh of, doth not properly apperteine to vſurie: for there the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was only, whether it might be brought to paſſe, that a man not being lord and owner of them, might yet take fruite and profitte of thoſe thinges whiche are waſted with the vſing. And when the lawyers had deuiſed, that it ſhould be done, as it might be done: that is, with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5452:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a prouiſo, to reſtore agayne the value of the thing after a certayne time: they dyd then deuiſe no more, but howe he that had the vſe of the thinge, might in the meane tyme be dettor of yt for the lordes ſafegard, to whom the proprietie belonged: not adding, that he ſhould pay any thinge for the vſe of that whereof he was dettor: for that is an other queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and we ſhal ſee hereafter howe yt may be determined.</p>
               <p>Firſt lette vs agree herevpon, that it is in truth and in nature im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible, to diuide the vſe of thoſe thinges which are geuen to lone from the proprietie and ownor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of them. But the ciuil lawe deuiſed a ſhift, that the lord and ownor receauing a caution for the valew, ſhould ſuffer him to whom the profit was aſsigned, to enioy
<pb facs="tcp:5452:58"/>
the thing fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckly and freely in the meane ſeaſon. Now this Caution which was geuen to the lord and ownor of thoſe thinges, did ſtand to him in ſtead of his propriety. But if we looke to the truth it ſelf, the lorde hath for the tyme loſt the propriety of the oyle, corne, wine, or monie, whiche he delyuered to the vſufructuarie: for the vſe and proprietie of them can not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated.</p>
               <p>If the Ciuill lawe ſawe and confeſſed this muche, what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhifte or prouiſo yt made to frame the matter otherwyſe: once yt was not done accordinge to truthe, but by wittie meanes and counterpeyſes, whiche were not vnlawful, ſo long as no man had iniurie by them. For the name on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being changed, yt might haue bene ſayed thus: If any man will
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5452:58"/>
bequeath the vſe and fruite of wyne, oyle, or monie: the heyer or executour ſhalbe bounde, to lende the legatarie ſo muche vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon an obligation, to haue the ſame quantitie reſtored at hys death or otherwiſe as the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth. And ſeeing this were an honeſt legacie, the other alſo may haue an honeſt meaning, if yt be ſayed: I bequeathe the vſe and fruite of twentie poundes to ſuch a man during his life. Neither doth this proue any whit, that vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie was allowed by the ciuil lawe, but rather that yt was iudged for an impoſsible thing, if none other thing be done beſydes that, which the lawe of nature and of nations hath determined.</p>
               <p>What ſay we then? Doth not the Ciuill lawe permitte vſurie? I aunſwer, that yt permitteth
<pb facs="tcp:5452:59"/>
yt not as a thing that can aryſe of the contract of geuing to lone: but expreſſely teacheth, that vſurie muſt be ſette about by an other way, or ells yt can not be brought to paſſe at al<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that other way whereof the ciuil lawe ſpeaketh, is not able to diſcharge any mans conſcience who ſhal take vppon him to follow yt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In Pande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis lib. <hi>5.</hi> Si ti dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
                  <hi>Proculus</hi> the lawyer writeth thus: <hi>If I geue or delyuer thee tenne thowſand, and bargaine that thou ſhalt owe me twenty thowſand: there ariſeth no obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any more then in tenne thowſand. Re enim non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt obligatio contrahi, niſi quatenus datu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit.</hi> For an obligation can not be made, touching a thing, but ſo far foorth as it is delyuered. For when a man is bound by the dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of the thinge yt ſelfe (as yt cometh to paſſe in geuing to lone)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5452:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the obligation can be none other, then as farre as the thing was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or delyuered.</p>
               <p>Lykewiſe <hi>Vlpian</hi> writeth:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>11.</hi> in Pandectis de rebus creditis.</note> 
                  <hi>Si de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem dedero, vt vndecim debeas, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus putat, amplius quàm decem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dici non poſſe.</hi> If I geue or delyuer tenne, for this end, to make thee dettor of eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Proculus</hi> thinketh, that no more can be certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded but tenne.</p>
               <p>Marke, in what ſort theſe men ſpeake. <hi>There can be no obligation of dette aboue the ſumme that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered.</hi> Which thing ſith yt is ſo, doubtleſſe there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vſury, no, not ſo much as by the ciuil lawe in the contract of ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to lone. For in vſurie the dettor is bound (at the leaſt in the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vſurer) to reſtore more then he tooke Yea farther I ſaye, that any ſuch obligation, whereby
<pb facs="tcp:5452:60"/>
more then was delyuered ſhould be looked for, is not only not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the contract of geuing to lone: but it is alſo againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that contract.</p>
               <p>For if it were not againſt the nature thereof by a bargaine made at the tyme of the contracte, it would be ſo annexed and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated to the contracte, that yt ſhould be accompted a part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For the lawyers confeſſe, that what ſoeuer bargaines (not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to that which is in hand) are made at the tyme of couenanting or of deliuerie, ſhal ſtand for good, and the performance of them may be required by the proper action of the ſame contract. But ſeeing when I delyuer tenne to lone, and bargayne for twenty, I can not demaunde twentie by the ſame action, whereby I demaund the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5452:60"/>
tenne whiche I delyuered: yt is cleere, that the bargaine for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was ſuche, as could neuer be graffed in the former contracte of geuing to lone. What then? ſhall not vſurie be couenaunted for, and alſo be demaunded in iudgement by the Ciuill lawe? Yeas. But that muſt not be done by the force of geuing to lone, nor by any bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne depending therevpon, or adioyned vnto yt. How then? for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth ther muſt be a forme of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des conceaued beſides the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract of geuing to lone, in the whiche forme of wordes the borower ſhal anſwer and by promiſſe bind him ſelfe, to geue for ſuch a ſumme thus much by the moneth, or by the yeare.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ecta, in Pandectis ſi certum petatur.</note> And then by the ciuil lawe an action ſhalbe geuen againſt hym that promiſed ſuche vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: An action, I ſay, not of lone,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:61"/>
but of the ſolemne obligation or bond of wordes.</p>
               <p>Thus the matter was patched vp betwene the infidels in the old tyme. But if we ſhalbe as men ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by reaſon, what other thing in natural truth was that ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne form of wordes, then a mere bargaine? What ſkilleth it, whether at the delyuerie of the tenne poundes, I ſay, (wel ſir, here are tenne, but if you keepe them this whole yeare, you ſhal render me twelue poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des for them: and ſo euerie yeare, after the rate, fortie ſhillinges for them, and he ſayth, he is content) Or ells, how ſay you ſir, wil you geue me fortie ſhillinges for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie yeare, wherein this ten pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des is not reſtored? He anſwereth yea. In truth and natural honeſtie the former bargaine differeth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the later<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet by the former I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5452:61"/>
had not bene bound, and by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I am. Why ſo? Becauſe yt ſo pleaſed the Citizens of Rome: who would no man to be bound by his bare wordes, excepte they were conceaued in a ſolemne forme of aſking and anſweringe. And by that forme vſurie might be couenanted for, and was made due. Wherby we gaine no farther, but that the wiſemen and lawiers cenfeſsing vſurie to be againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet would haue yt to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, not by the lawe of nature, whence al good and right lawe is deriued, but only by the lawe of Rome, which when yt is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the lawe of nature, is no lawe, but only an Idol or falſe pretence of lawe.</p>
               <p>And yet thoſe Infidel Romans were ſo wiſe, and ſo naturally ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, as to confeſſe that vſurie
<pb facs="tcp:5452:62"/>
could not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by nature, although being otherwiſe ouercomed by couetouſnes, they ſought how to make yt lawefull emong them. And ſo is yt fulfilled whiche S. Paule ſayed of them:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Whereas they had knowen God by his creatures, they did not glorifie him as God: but vaniſhed away in their owne fooliſh deuiſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>doing thoſe thinges which them ſelues condemned as vnlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But touching that which we had principally to proue, the ciuil wiſemen of Rome did not allowe vſurie, as a thing that either did na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally belong to the contracte of geuing to lone, or els that might be annexed thereunto: but they permitted it otherwiſe, as alſo thei did permitte fornication and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorſes. And yet the ſtate of an vſurer is ſo muche worſe then the ſtate of a fornicator or of a harlot,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5452:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
becauſe although the fornicatour or harlot happen to make any filthie gayne by ſetting their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies out to hyer: yet they are bounde to penaunce onely, and to the recompenſe of ſuche ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as they haue fallen into. But they are not bound to reſtore that monie which they tooke for their vile ſeruice. For as the lawyer ſaieth: <hi>Turpiter fecit ꝙ ſit meretrix,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dict. ob turpem cauſam lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſed non turpiter accipit cùm ſit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retrix.</hi> The harlot doth filthyly in being an harlot: but ſeing ſhe is an harlot, ſhe taketh not her wagies filthiely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is to ſay, by a filthy trade ſhe yet maketh the monie her owne, as the which is due to her, when once ſhe hath played the harlot.</p>
               <p>But the vſurer doth not make the vſury his own at al, but he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to reſtore yt to him, of whome
<pb facs="tcp:5452:63"/>
he tooke yt, as if he had ſtolen ſo much from him.</p>
               <p>But now the men with whom we diſpute, wil needes haue vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be a reaſonable contract by the lawe of nature, becauſe they thinke that their owne monie is vſed, and therefore that rent is due to them for yt. Wherein they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians are more groſſely deceaued, then euer the philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers or ciuil lawyers were, both which wel ſawe, that no ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract could ſtand in nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.</note>But as God geuing the two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles vnto <hi>Moyſes</hi> vpon the mount Sinay, did in maner nothing elles, but renew agayne the lawe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which was in maner worne out of the Iſralites hartes thorow euil education and cuſtome: euen ſo Chriſt came into the world, to geue vs grace, whereby the ſayd
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5452:63"/>
lawe of nature might be both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly knowen, and ſufficiently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of his members and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes: That lawe of nature, I ſay, which was at the beginning, and which was not corrupted by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular cuſtomes or lawes of euil men: that lawe which forbiddeth fornication, manie wiues, diuorſes, vſurie, Simonie, and ſuch like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, as are nowe growen in vſe emong corrupted men.</p>
               <p>He therefore, that either ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth or hoapeth for vſurie vppon that which is geuen to lone, is not of Abels common weale, or a member of Chriſte (except he reconcile him ſelfe by dooing due pennaunce) but he is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale of Caine, whence the inuention of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe lawes and earthly cuſtomes came.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:64"/>If thou wilt be wiſe in God, make him thy dettor: putte thy monie into his handes, who will laye it vp in heauen for thee, and wil geue thee vſury and ouerplus for it.<note place="margin">Prou. c. <hi>19</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Foeneratur Domino, qui miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur pauperis, &amp; viciſsitudinem ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reddet ei.</hi> He that taketh pitie of the poore, geueth his mony to God vppon vſurie, and God will geue him his recompence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Certaine examples of vſurie, vvhereby yt may the better be knovven, vvhat is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and vvhat is not and of the reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvhich the vſurer is bound to make. The x. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>IF vſurie be ſo contrarie (as yt hath bene ſhewed) to the moſt excellent vertue of almoſdedes, and to the moſt charitable contract of geuing to lone: what remaineth but that thoſe who are hitherto
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5452:64"/>
free from that vice, ſhould nowe the more deteſt it: and thoſe who by ignorance or frailtie are fallen into yt, ſhould repent and make reſtitution of that which was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully gotten.</p>
               <p>But for ſo much as euerie man is not able to vnderſtand the general doctrine of vſury, vnleſſe it be moſt euidently opened vnto him: I thought good, to make the matter yet more playne by certaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and caſes as foloweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt (as I haue ſhewed before) al that is vſurie, which is bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for, or taken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aboue the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal which was geuen to lone.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, vſurie conſiſteth not only in mony, but alſo in corne, wine, oyle, or any other thing that is geuen to lone, as yf I lend two buſhels of corne at Eaſter, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue three for it at harueſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Not onely the takinge of any thing aboue the principal, but alſo the looking for yt, though yt be not taken, doth make him guyltie before God, who looketh or hoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth for yt, by the reaſon of the lone. I ſay, he is therby guyltie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: but he is bound to make no real reſtitution if he take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But yt is otherwiſe, if any man geue or offer any thing, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the lone, but to ſhew him ſelf mindful of a good turne recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. For that which is ſo offered, may be lawfully take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without any vſury committed: ſo that there be no fraude vſed therin, but that the intent and conſcience of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauer be vpright and free in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> When the borower vſeth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yearely, or quarterly, or at
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5452:65"/>
certaine tymes, to geue alwaies one certaine thinge, and that alſo in monie: yt worthely maketh the receauer to be ſuſpected as an vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. And therefore yt were not good ſo to do, if yt were but for the ſauing of a mans good name, and for the auoyding of ſlaunders and offences. But yet whether the receauer be in dede an vſurer or no before God, it dependeth alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gethers vpon his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience: which if it looke not for the brybe, and likewiſe if he lent not his monie for that end, or leaue not the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny therefore in the others handes: he may be free from the vice of vſurie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> I can not eaſely deuiſe, how he ſhould be excuſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſurie, who though he bargaine for no gaynes, yet not tarrieng till his monie or ſtuffe be borowed of him, ſeeketh
<pb facs="tcp:5452:66"/>
out a merchaunt of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord by whome yt may be vſed: and taketh what ſo euer the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt offereth him yearely. For his deede ſeemeth to importe a mental vſurie: except he ſeeke him out only for charities ſake, becauſe he would not haue his monie lye by him idle, whereas yt may do an other man good.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> If I hauing to do in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and therefore cauſing the value of my monie to be made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by a bill of exchaunge, do let my mony lye in the exchaungers hand, to th'end I may receaue more in euerie pound, then the iuſt value by exchaunge cometh to (whiche is called geuing to vſance) it is the vice of vſurie. For the length of the tyme can neuer be any iuſt cauſe, why I ſhould receaue more then I dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5452:66"/>
ſith it is ſtraight his monie who receaueth yt, and yt ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth at his perill. And therefore he payeth me for the vſe of his owne, which is vniuſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Who ſo ſelleth his wares the derer, onely becauſe the monie is not payed him out of hande, requireth that ouerplus of monie onely for the tymes ſake, and that is a kynde of vſurie. For yf the ſeller, who ſhould haue receaued (for example ſake) fourtie ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges for his oxe, demaund ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nobles, becauſe he ſhall not be payed before the quarter day: he dothe (as it were) lende the bier fourtie ſhillinges for ſo longe tyme, to receaue for it one noble ouerplus, whiche is euident v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The lyke is, if contrarie wiſe I owing one hundred poundes at a
<pb facs="tcp:5452:67"/>
certaine day, do pay tenne poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the leſſe, only becauſe I paie it before the day. For the monie which at the day ſhould be due, is as it were lent for ſo long vpon ten poundes in the hundred.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> He that bying a pece of ground vnder the price, afterward ſetteth yt foorth to be hyered of the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, in ſuch ſorte that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue (for examples ſake) fyue or ſix in the hundred aboue that which he gaue, committeth vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For although yt be lawfull to receaue gaines and re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of a mans owne landes: yet this land was not iuſtly the byers, but rather he lent his monie for vſurie, and cloaked the matter with the name of bying.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> If I lend monie vpon the pledge of certaine groundes or howſes, taking vp in the meane tyme the fruites of the ſame groundes or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5452:67"/>
howſes, and afterward receaue my principal againe, yt is vſurie. For I ought to take the fruites no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then til I haue my own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in that caſe not to receaue any other monie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the reſt is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly taken. But thoſe are only to be accompted fruites whiche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, al iuſt burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s excepted and debated.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Euerie daunger of the monie or cauſe of doubt, doth not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the vice of vſurie, except the daunger or doubt doo conſiſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that which may happen in the price of the thing it ſelfe, then in the only reſpect of tyme. For who ſo euer taketh ouerplus in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of tyme only that an other keepeth his monie, though he be content to aduenture the peril of carrieng that monie ouer the ſea, yet he thereby auoydeth not vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb facs="tcp:5452:68"/>
becauſe his bargaine groundeth vpon the gaines of that time wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the mony is none of his owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> When any man hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vſurie, he is bound to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to him, or his heires, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, of whom he tooke that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt gaines: except the partie that hath right to that mony, do freely and without al conſtraint or circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention forgeue the det. But who ſo wilbe ſure that he is forgeuen, I counſel him firſt of al, to take his principal out of the merchauntes hand, without putting him in hope to haue it againe, leaſt if he aſke forgeuenes whileſt the monie ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his handes, he do force the merchant to forgeue hym, who feareth if he ſhould not ſo do, he ſhould no longer enioy the mony<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hauing take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, hath the det afterward freely
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:5452:68"/>
forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: then would I exhort him alſo, rather to lette the honeſt merchant freely to vſe his mony, then that it ſhould lye idle by him.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I briefly geuen (as it were) a taſt of the matter of vſury: As minding to prouoke him that before thought litle thereof, to be hereafter the more carefull and feareful leaſt he abuſe the contract of geuing to lone, which God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for the great benefit of our poore neighbours. And by theſe few examples (but ſpecially by the reaſons wherby vſury was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the vij. chapter) the reader may coniecture, when he is in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of vſury, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. And when al other knowledge fayleth, he may aſke counſel of ſome learned and diſcreete man, who is hable to ſhewe him that, whiche lacketh in this Treatiſe.
<pb facs="tcp:5452:69"/>
For my chiefe purpoſe herein was only to ſhew, how great a vice vſurie is euen according to the lawe of nature, and howe warie and careful men ought to be in auoyding and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing the ſame.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:69"/>
            <p>Scriptum hoc de vſura lectum &amp; approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt à viris ſacrae Theologiae &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glici idiomatis peritiſsimis. quare tutò euulgari &amp; imprimi poſſe Iudico.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Cunerus Petri, Paſtor S. Petri Louanij,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>8.</hi> April. An. <hi>1568.</hi>
                  </date>
ſtylo communi ſeu Romano.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:70"/>
            <head>THE CHAPITERS, and Contentes of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The firſt Chapiter.THE occaſion of this Treatiſe, and the argumentes which are commonly made for the defence of vſury, and what is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. fol. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. That vſurie is forbidden by Gods law vnder the paine of euerlasting damnation. fol. 3. b.</item>
               <item>3. Whence bargaines procede, and why Almoſdeedes are ſo acceptable to God. fol. <hi>8.</hi> a.</item>
               <item>4. Of geuinge to lone, or of lendinge, which are naturally free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes. fol. <hi>13.</hi> b.</item>
               <item>5. How much it importeth, that the boundes and limites of euerie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract belonging to the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhould be inuiolably kept and maintayned. fol. <hi>22.</hi> b.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5452:70"/>6. That the vſurer in ſetting out his mony for gayne, doth, and can not but geue his mony to lone. fol. <hi>28.</hi> a</item>
               <item>7. How heynouſe, and how much againſt the nature of geuing to lone, and againſt the law of al Nations the vice of vſurie is. fol. <hi>33.</hi> a.</item>
               <item>8. That the Heathens condemned vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. fo. 50. b.</item>
               <item>9. That the Ciuil lawe doth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge vſurie to ſpring or ariſe of the nature of ſuch things as are geuen to lone, but rather to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie thereunto. fol. 53 a</item>
               <item>10. Certaine examples of vſurie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by yt may the better be knowen, what is vſurie, and what is not: and of the restitution which the vſurer is bound to make. fol. 62. b</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:71"/>
            <head>
               <hi>FAVLTES ESCAPED</hi> in printing.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Faultes</cell>
                     <cell>Pag.</cell>
                     <cell>Lin.</cell>
                     <cell>Corrections.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>it to</cell>
                     <cell>14. b.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>it is to.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ſeemeth the</cell>
                     <cell>24. a.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>ſerueth the</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And the</cell>
                     <cell>40. a.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>And as the</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is to</cell>
                     <cell>41. b.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>It is to</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>of ge-to</cell>
                     <cell>50. a.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>of geuing to</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:71"/>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:72"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  <p>RESPICITE VOLATILIA COELI, ET PVLLOS CORVORVM</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5452:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
